<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/3.1.4" created="2014-09-10 10:52" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.1/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.1/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Schacht Aslani Architects Blog</title>
	<link>http://saarch.com/blog</link>
	<description></description>
	<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 10:52:07 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.1</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://saarch.com/blog</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>http://saarch.com/blog</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>1</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>admin</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>marshall@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Marshall Turner]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Marshall]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Turner]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>5</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>chris</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>chris@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Chris Taucher]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Chris]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Taucher]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>6</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>cima</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>cima@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Cima Malek-Aslani]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Cima]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Malek-Aslani]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>7</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>evan</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>evan@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Evan Bourquard]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Evan]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Bourquard]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>8</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>jonathan</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>jonathan@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Jonathan French]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Jonathan]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[French]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>9</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>shazi</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>shazi@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Shazi Tharian]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Shazi]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Tharian]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>10</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>walter</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>walter@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Walter Schacht]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Walter]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Schacht]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>
	<wp:author><wp:author_id>14</wp:author_id><wp:author_login>neil</wp:author_login><wp:author_email>neil@saarch.com</wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[neil]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Neil]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Parrish]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>


	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.1.4</generator>

	<item>
		<title>Reshaping Teaching &amp; Learning</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/07/23/reshaping-teaching-learning/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 23:22:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>cima</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=7</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs) are on their way to changing the delivery of higher education. Just last week Coursera, the for-profit startup that currently offers MOOCs for free, announced that twelve major research universities including University of Washington had joined their open courseware venture. Again, articles in the press used the words “seismic shift” and “tsunami” relative to the effect MOOCs are having on higher education. In May when the Harvard/MIT open courseware project was announced, planners at the University of Washington voiced guarded interest and noted the many questions surrounding MOOCs ability to truly disrupt higher education. Two months later, however, the UW is partnering with Coursera to deliver courses via MOOCs. With the UW and other major research universities joining the open courseware movement “seismic shift” still sounds extreme but it is clear that change is accelerating.

<!--more-->What does the open courseware movement mean for the architecture of buildings for higher education? Online/e-learning will change teaching and learning and the roles of faculties, and that impacts learning environments. MOOCs, as they are evolving, are proving to be an effective form of delivering content as they are more interactive and conducive to learning. Research is showing that this interactive form of online learning is as effective as the traditional lecture format. And when five thousand students enrolled in a MOOC make the same mistake online, professors can immediately adjust the way material is being taught. Research also shows that learning models which are a blend of online and in-person classes are more effective than the traditional lecture format where students passively listen to delivery of content.

In discussions with UW Associate Dean Kevin Mihata and with Renee Carney, eLearning Manager at Lower Columbia College, (where we are involved in facility master planning) the open courseware movement will require faculty to acquire new skills. The need for “instructional designers” was noted by both educators. Renae noted that unlike K-12 teachers trained in the science of education, higher education instructors are trained solely in content with content typically delivered in lecture format. New skills based on the science of education, how students learn, and how skills are evaluated will need to be acquired by faculty. As Kevin Mihata noted, in contrast with the lecture format, contact time with students becomes interactive time in blended models. These developments indicate potential outcomes of the open courseware movement.

The changing roles of instructors and pedagogies are impacting the way we are planning facilities for our current community college client, Lower Columbia College. For academic transfer programs which prepare students for upper division learning at four-year institutions, online learning brings into question the need for the lecture hall. If the large lecture hall is no longer necessary, we need to evaluate the proper size classroom that allows flexibility for emerging pedagogies and blended learning models. Furniture and technology play into this discussion as does the number of students the classroom should serve with these pedagogies.

In workforce education, if content is delivered through e-learning, less space will be required for the traditional classroom and master planning could focus on the proper lab environments that convert that knowledge into skills required by employers. And adjacencies of spaces that facilitate informal as well as formal learning must be considered for all programs. When the business model for delivering higher education changes as it will, the facilities that serve higher-ed will change along with it. As designers and planners we must anticipate these changes.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>7</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-07-23 15:22:33</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-23 23:22:33</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>reshaping-teaching-learning</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="education"><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="online-learning"><![CDATA[Online Learning]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Change &amp; Disruption</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/07/16/change-disruption/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 23:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>cima</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=11</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Much has been written about the Great Disruption of higher education driven by the open courseware movement. The discussion has recently ramped up again with the announcement that Harvard and MIT will be putting their courses online, and with the emergence of two for-profit startups headed by Stanford University faculty. The open courseware movement has been around for at least ten years when MIT first put its courses online but the question still is when and how this Great Disruption will actually take place. As further evidence, the Society for College and University Planning (SCUP) will be taking up Change-Disruption in the March 2013 issue of Planning for Higher Education. As architects whose focus and passion is designing learning environments for higher education we are monitoring these changes.

<!--more-->Considering music and print media, industries that were disrupted by the Internet, there were issues of supply and demand that controlled the speed of change. The low barriers to entry on the Internet allowed alternative supply models to emerge quickly and cheaply, dramatically changing the business model for these industries. With higher education, we have not seen that rate of change, primarily because the suppliers still control the means of admission and accreditation which are valued components for students and their future employers. But there is evidence that change is happening as others are increasingly contributing to the supply side.

I recently met with Dr. Kevin Mihata, Associate Dean for Educational Programs at the University of Washington, to discuss the impact of Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs) on the UW’s thinking about the delivery of higher education. While we discussed a variety of issues related to this subject, the issue of “brand” is one that appears to be driving change at the top. Now that more elite institutions are becoming involved in the open courseware movement others are taking notice and getting into the game, including top tier public universities.

Elite institutions will not likely dilute a solid brand by giving degrees online to the masses. They will, however, undoubtedly learn much about pedagogy from MOOCs which will only strengthen their brand for the future. One of the for-profit startups, Coursera, partners with institutions to host courses online. Stanford University, University of California Berkeley, University of Michigan, Princeton and University of Pennsylvania have all signed up with Coursera. University of Washington is considering its options with respect to joining the open courseware movement.

While being on the cutting edge of pedagogy through MOOCs drives institutions at the top to change, back door means, driven by motivated students and faculty are emerging and will drive change from the bottom up. Founded in 2007, the Community College Consortium for Open Educational Resources strives to work with faculty to improve teaching and learning while increasing educational access using open educational resources. Another consortium, the Open Courseware Consortium, promotes the adoption of open educational recourses and shares best practices. Motivated students who gain knowledge through online means and then pass a test or demonstrate skills through alternate presentation methods could drive change in the way parts of curriculum are delivered. With private for-profits linked with elite institutions exploring the means to deliver cost effective and accredited courses, and consortiums of public institutions working to increase access to higher education through online resources, changes in the supply side will eventually affect the business model for higher education. Change linked with technology always happens faster than expected and we are entering that cycle with higher education.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>11</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-07-16 15:23:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-07-16 23:23:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>change-disruption</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="education"><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="online-learning"><![CDATA[Online Learning]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Vision &amp; Change</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/06/20/vision-change/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2012 23:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>cima</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=13</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The last session of the 2012 CEFPI Pacific Northwest Regional Conference introduced the concept of pre-design for K-12 schools. The design of K-12 schools must respond to rapidly changing expectations for teaching and learning. In this context pre-design has value as a step in the design process. The presentation focused on the steps that should be part of a K-12 pre-design starting with discovery and visioning as precedents to planning and testing programmatic concepts. Discovery involves an information gathering process that leads collaboratively to a vision for the proposed project. Thus the stakeholders have ownership of the vision, which is critical if the vision changes the way people are used to doing things.

<!--more-->Our experience with designing the <a href="http://saarch.com/ocee.php">Opportunity Center for Employment and Education</a> (OCEE) supports this notion. pre-design, which is mandated for public higher education facilities, had real value in linking the discovery process with vision. For the OCEE the process just happened in reverse order as the vision for a new service model for delivery of employment, education, and social services on a community college campus envisioned by Speaker of the House, Frank Chopp, preceded the information gathering and discovery exercises. The pre-design was then a process of vetting that vision with the public agencies that would implement this vision on a day to day basis. It was not the easy route but it did get the project moving forward as many of the agencies’ concerns were addressed in pre-design. The agencies also saw the benefits of the proposed project and there was no backtracking in later design phases. Now after a year of occupying the finished building, the agencies in the OCEE are working collaboratively with success to implement the new service model.

New methods of teaching and learning are not always embraced by the teachers that have to implement them as was presented in the session on British Columbia’s 21st Century Learning Initiative. As a result the architects had to be creative in designing schools with “one foot in the 20th century and the other in the 21st.” A pre-design process that linked the vision which came from above (the Superintendant’s office) with a discovery process of what that vision could achieve for teaching and learning could have been of value in implementing the well researched learning initiative with teachers.

Change is a constant in our world today and it is often hard to accept. Vision and change often go hand in hand. Vision that comes from above is at times necessary in order to move new ideas forward. A pre-design process that explores the benefits as well as the concerns that inevitably come with changing expectations for teaching and learning could benefit school districts, the community, architects, and the teachers who are on the front lines for educating our children.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>13</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-06-20 15:24:05</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-20 23:24:05</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>vision-change</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="education"><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="online-learning"><![CDATA[Online Learning]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The Impact of Online Learning on Planning &amp; Design</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/08/07/the-impact-of-online-learning-on-planning-design/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2012 23:26:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>cima</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=15</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Our approach to the campus master plan for Lower Columbia College and the design of a new arts and health occupations building at Olympic College reflect the impact of Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs) on higher education. Lower Columbia’s master plan considers changing role of the campus in education as the capacity of open, online courses to reduce the need for lecture-based classes to take place at the College. Spaces that accommodate experiential learning will become a focus of the campus. In workforce education, for example, general content will probably be delivered online. Vocational labs will be designed to simulate workplace environments, enabling students to engage in skills development allows them to prepare for employment.

<!--more-->

Classrooms will be designed as active learning spaces, promoting face-to-face engagement, taking advantage of digital tools and online resources, and serving the needs of hybrid courses. Classroom sizes, instructional technology, furniture and equipment will be evaluated as part of the process. Campus-wide technology infrastructure to support online learning will be a fundamental component of the master plan.

Lower Columbia College’s library, which has already changed from a place for quiet, individual study to a space that accommodates interactive learning and group study, will continue to evolve. In the future it needs to support collaborative, project based learning and provide places for students who meet through online peer review to get together in person. Coursera’s programs reveal that online connections between students enrolled in a MOOC encourage person-to-person meetings. Coursera’s founders planned a party for students who completed their first course and discovered that a thousand students wanted to attend.

The College Instruction Center will provide space for Olympic College’s fine arts, music, performing arts and health occupations programs. The mission of the project is to create a facility that brings all of its students together to create a community of learners.

The building is organized in plan and section to give each discipline a sense of place and promote efficiency for students, faculty and staff. The public spaces in the building are designed to create connections between the programs, encouraging interaction between disciplines. Atrium spaces and open stairwells allow views through the building that create a sense of the whole. Transparency, both inside and out, makes each program visible, engaging people in the dynamic activity that occurs in the building – making art, making music, working in health occupations skills labs. In a sense all of the programs share a vocational orientation due to the hands-on nature of their learning environments. Informal student study spaces are located in proximity to the stairs that connect the building vertically. These “hub zones” provide places for students to assemble in small groups, work on projects and share ideas. They provide the social spaces that will be a magnet for coming to campus in the evolving model of higher education.

At the capital request and predesign phases the project included a 75 seat lecture hall. During the schematic design, the fixed seat space is being replaced by smaller, more flexible, flat floor learning environments. An active learning lab that will serve all of the programs is being designed to facilitate group work on projects and one-to-one engagement between students and faculty. The space will be located on the ground floor of the building, directly connected to the lobby where it is highly visible and easily accessed.

The future of higher education, in the age of MOOCs both challenges and stimulates administrators, faculty, staff and students to rethink the nature of the learning experience. The role of a physical campus will be transformed as a result. At the same time, a fundamental aspect of the academic experience is being reaffirmed. The role of an academic campus as a place that fosters interaction, promotes dialogue and makes palpable a sense of community is likely to be at the heart of planning and design for the future.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>15</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-08-07 15:26:05</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-08-07 23:26:05</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>the-impact-of-online-learning-on-planning-design</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="education"><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="online-learning"><![CDATA[Online Learning]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>BIM Philosophy</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/01/04/bim-philosophy/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 23:34:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>evan</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=20</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[When a small firm undertakes a big change, such as changing the way they document their projects, great care must be taken to execute that upgrade without fundamentally altering the way they practice or affecting the quality of their documentation. I thought I might take a moment to share a few thoughts on the “fun” part of the changeover process at Schacht Aslani Architects: developing our office philosophy towards the use of Building Information Modeling (BIM) and how fellow staff member Casey Borgen and I wrote the office manual for the use of REVIT.

<!--more-->

Like many firms, over the last decade our office has charged forward into the Building Information Modeling arena. Building Information Modeling (BIM) is a real paradigm shift in the way architects think about and document design projects in development. Unlike other 3D visualization software that emerged a decade or so ago (like Sketchup and 3D Studio MAX), a true BIM model allows architects to fully model 3D elements of a building in real time. We construct the building using intelligent components that contain real information (like materials or identity data) and that interact intelligently with one another. From this virtual model or database, we then extract the traditional 2D representations of a project (plans, sections, elevations, and details) that we need to communicate with the contractor and upon which our contractual obligations are based. From a user standpoint this is an amazing transformation, as we now use more of our time “building” a project, and less time executing rote drawing operations.

When developing our REVIT Manual and office standards, here are a few fundamental thoughts that we used to organize our work:

Don’t try to teach everything. There is already a vast collection of resources and voices available to provide basic how-to assistance with the REVIT program. So in the manual we decided NOT to try to explain or teach basic operations of the REVIT program. That accomplishes two important things: first it allows new staff to bring new ideas and practices into the office, and second it saves time because we aren’t chasing small tweaks to the manual to keep it up to date with the development of the program itself. The document assumes baseline knowledge of the program and focusses on what makes our use of the program unique.
<ol>
	<li>Answer “How Should I” instead of “How Do I”. The primary purpose of the REVIT Manual is to establish the unique and specific methodology that is to be used on our projects. Instead of answering the question, “How do I do x?” this document mostly deals with, “How should I do x?” This creates a framework for what we feel are best practices when dealing with certain difficult issues, like modeling casework or drawing details. By setting some basic guidelines for how users in the office should tackle complex problems, we have more flexibility with staffing later phases and more consistency in the final product.</li>
	<li>Organization is the key the efficiency. In addition to setting Revit standards, the Manual also addresses some peripheral issues, including basic folder and project organization, and provides examples of SAA graphic formats. This helps keep teams on track in terms of finding and quickly using information generated by others, and makes adjustments to graphic look and feel easier to accomplish office-wide. It also helps non-users locate and use project information as the structure stays consistent across projects. Project examples and graphic identity examples are commonly located for everyone to use.</li>
	<li>Darwin was right. Like all living things, businesses need to evolve to stay alive and relevant. Just because we develop a document on how SAA staff should use REVIT doesn’t mean we’ve completed solved a problem. In addition to a strong culture of collaboration that already exists in the office, to prevent stagnation we bring all the REVIT users together for monthly training sessions. These are part update on portions of the manual, part presentation by project teams on how they solved a specific problem or issues, and part REVIT therapy. The informal format allows new programs, uses and techniques to be disseminated to the rest of the user group organically, and provides a space for the community of users to talk about and refine our office philosophy.</li>
	<li>It’s only a tool. At SAA we pride ourselves on the quality of our design and deliverables. The use of a new program or process can’t fundamentally change what we want to accomplish in terms of design or sustainability on our projects. Our office focuses heavily on iterative design and the development of multiple options simultaneously that are then evaluated together. The REVIT Manual includes chapters on the best ways to organize and use the program to generate and track these design options. This allows our office to continue to practice the way that we want to, and not the other way around.</li>
	<li>K.I.S.S. Keeping it simple is the best way to make sure that the REVIT document will stay relevant. If it is too complex, it will not be updated and will no longer be a useful tool. Organized the manual by chapter and including “how-to” sections allows us to focus on specific tasks. By focusing on the philosophy behind the decisions of the various issues in the chapters, we avoid being bogged down trying to explain compound operations.</li>
</ol>
I’ve included a snapshot of our REVIT manual table of contents to give you a visual on the organization of the document. Also attached are a few “out of the box” 3d views of current projects that I thought I would share to show you what we can do with the program.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>20</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-04 15:34:53</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-04 23:34:53</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>bim-philosophy</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="bim"><![CDATA[BIM]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Automating a Construction Time-Lapse</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/11/19/automating-a-construction-time-lapse/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2012 00:55:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=32</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The great IT staff at North Seattle Community College recently set up <a href="https://northseattle.edu/about-north/new-construction">three webcams</a> watching the construction of the new Technology Building. The building renovation will provide space for labs and classrooms for the College's health, medical and science programs: creating a Human Biology and Science Center including a lab for anatomy, physiology and biology with an intergraded prep area; a Learning Center to centralize and consolidate the College's tutoring programs and promote student success; a Food Services function; and space for student gathering.

We wanted to use these cameras to assemble of a time-lapse of the entire construction, without spending extra money or having to work with the College to get things set up. After some research, we found out a quick and simple way to automate the process. We'd like to share what we found, in case anyone is looking to do the same.

The problem is that the AXIS webcam that the College uses outputs the image in MJPG format, which doesn't save single frames nicely. We could parse the raw image data and extract one from there, but that would be a lot of work. After some research, we found that the webcam had a "snapshot" feature that would give a single JPEG. Unfortunately, the College hadn't turned the feature on, so the button to do so was missing. Digging through the webcam manual, we learned we could append "/axis-cgi/jpg/image.cgi" to force-trigger the snapshot, and kick out the JPEG. Next, we had to set up our computer to grab the image daily, preferably at the same time. We wrote a batch file, containing the following lines:
<blockquote>wget http://axis-cam1.northseattle.edu/axis-cgi/jpg/image.cgi -O C:\Users\marshall\Documents\timelapse\%date:~10,4%%date:~4,2%%date:~7,2%-camera1.jpg wget http://axis-cam2.northseattle.edu/axis-cgi/jpg/image.cgi -O C:\Users\marshall\Documents\timelapse\%date:~10,4%%date:~4,2%%date:~7,2%-camera2.jpg wget http://axis-cam3.northseattle.edu/axis-cgi/jpg/image.cgi -O C:\Users\marshall\Documents\timelapse\%date:~10,4%%date:~4,2%%date:~7,2%-camera3.jpg</blockquote>
Here's a quick breakdown, so you can use this on your own. The "wget" is a command that tells the computer to grab the image at the address that follows. The "-O" flag tells wget to output the image to the path that follows. The "%date:~10,4%%date:~4,2%%date:~7,2%" is a set of variables that outputs the date in YYYYMMDD format, and appends "-camera#.jpg" at the end. Windows Task Manager then was set up to trigger the script at noon every day. At the end, we'll compile those into the complete time lapse. Hopefully this helps if you're looking to do something similar.

<em><strong>**Update**</strong></em>

I also realized it'd be helpful to document how we assembled the images into a movie. We used the freeware utility <a href="http://www.ffmpeg.org/">ffmpeg</a> to take the single images that were outputted by the script above, and stich them into one movie. This command-line utility is our go-to for any heavy-duty video conversion, and it can do much much more than we're illustrating here.

The program works well when the images are labeled sequentially, so we used the awesome freeware <a href="http://www.bulkrenameutility.co.uk/Main_Intro.php">Bulk Rename Utility</a> to do so. Once the images were labeled "image001.jpg, image002.jpg, etc...", we started the command prompt.

After navigating to the folders with the images, we ran the following command.
<blockquote>ffmpeg -f image2 -r 6 -bufsize 500k -i image%d.jpg camera1.mp4</blockquote>
I won't go into too much detail about what the command does, but did want to highlight the "-r" flag. That is the framerate flag, and it tells ffmpeg to limit the movie to 6 frames a second. Otherwise, the time-lapse would zip by too quickly. That can be adjusted depending on your needs. We ran that for each folder of images, and it kicked out three separate movies.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>32</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-11-19 16:55:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-11-20 00:55:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>automating-a-construction-time-lapse</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Re: Un Limited Means Lecture by Alejandro Echeverri</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/11/14/re-un-limited-means-lecture-by-alejandro-echeverri/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 01:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>jonathan</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=35</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Myself and a few of the architects from Schacht Aslani recently attended <a href="http://alejandroecheverriarquitectos.tumblr.com/">Alejandro Echeverri</a>'s lecture at <a href="http://www.themakersspace.com/">The Maker's Space</a>, presented by <a href="http://spacecityseattle.org/">Space.City</a>.
<blockquote>via Space.City

"In addition to his strong architectural practice and teaching, as Director of Urban Projects, Echeverri has played crucial role in the rejuvenation of Medellin, Colombia. With the support and partnership of the city's mayor, Sergio Fajardo, Echeverri established public works programs and initiated building a series of visually striking libraries, schools, parks, and community centers in Medellin's most impoverished areas, including the an elevated gondola tramway that connects some of Medellin's poorest and most isolated neighborhoods to the rest of the city. Because of these efforts and the belief in the power of design, Medellin's crime rate has significantly declined and the city is now considered a blueprint for the future of other cities in the developing world."</blockquote>
<!--more-->To me, the on-going work in Medellin speaks to the breadth and complexity of acting positively and purposefully within the built environment. The people advocating for change in Medellin made a purposeful decision to look clearly at reality and map the city as both the formalized built spaces and the informal built spaces, and to direct their efforts towards the conditions of life at the informal edges. By analyzing the conditions of the city, the people pushing for change pursued infrastructural and cultural projects that stitch together zonas previously separated by topographical and territorial boundaries, creating new public spaces that are no longer controlled by drug cartels. It is inspiring to see politics and cultural values align so that design projects can enact such powerful change. However, it is also interesting to recognize that those conditions do not exist everywhere and that ultimately the projects will cause many different changes.

One of the questions raised during the discussion period addressed the nature of property ownership and rights, questioning how the creation of formalized public infrastructure and cultural centers in informal neighborhoods changes the property rights of the marginalized people who live in the surrounding area. There is no immediate answer, but the question again points to the complexity of the issue and to how fundamentally different Medellin is from a place like Seattle. Perhaps the best message I took away from the lecture is that the efforts in Medellin are doing their best to look clearly at reality and then opening their thinking to how those challenges can be addressed. How the process unfolds from there is undetermined, but to act creatively requires first seeing the conditions clearly.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>35</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-11-14 17:00:22</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-11-15 01:00:22</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>re-un-limited-means-lecture-by-alejandro-echeverri</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="lectures"><![CDATA[Lectures]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Brief Notes on the AIA CAE Conference</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/10/02/brief-notes-on-the-aia-cae-conference/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2012 01:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>shazi</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=38</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Cima and I recently attended the AIA's <a href="http://network.aia.org/committeeonarchitectureforeducation/home/">Committee on Architecture for Education</a> Fall Conference here in Seattle. The conference was designed to "elevate the level of discourse about design, environmental responsibility, teaching and learning, context, and the development of community partnerships in support of improving the country's learning environments." Very briefly, we wanted to give a few impressions of the conference, which we found quite engaging.

On the first day, one session in particular really stood out to us. The <a href="http://saarch.com/www.cedarriver.org">Friends of the Cedar River Watershed</a> are an amazing group of kids taking ownership of their environment, and getting the community involved and invested in sustainability, through service projects, curriculum development and short films that they make and screen at REI and online.

The event also gave us an opportunity to further develop our understanding of the evolving classroom in a time of great technological change. We started the conference talking about the classroom being just another context for learning, and ended with the idea of MOOC's and how learning and universities are extending their reach, and teaching on the Internet. Our context as architects used to be the physical surroundings for the building, now the physical has blended with the virtual, and the context we need to respond to goes beyond the immediate site. How can we make our buildings work for this new blended reality?]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>38</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-10-02 17:01:04</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-10-03 01:01:04</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>brief-notes-on-the-aia-cae-conference</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="education"><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="lectures"><![CDATA[Lectures]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>From the Site</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/09/11/from-the-site/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2012 01:01:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>chris</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=40</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[As architects we always hear that the relationship between the owner and architect is the key to a successful project. I agree that that is extremely important and crucial to the livelihood of our practice, but also believe that that there is another partner that is needed to make a project successful, and that is the Contractor. Without a strong relationship between the contractor and the architect, the owner's	vision cannot become reality.

At Schacht Aslani Architects we strive to develop a mutual respect between both professions with the understanding that we can both learn from each other. People get into each profession out of the love of craft; both have decide to put our minds and hands together to create and build. Our willingness to learn from the past and those who came before us has made us better at what we do. I continue to believe that we can continue to develop strong relationships based on this shared background, and work together to build better structures.

I have been in this business long enough to see the huge amount of evolution and change. Technology has changed how architects design and document buildings and how contractors manage and construct buildings. For example, technology has radically changed how we communicate with each other in the field. Days of faxing information back and forth during construction are extremely rare, if not non-existent. With this rise in efficiency, owners expect projects to be completed faster than ever before and on a tighter budget. Technology such as BIM, mobile devices, and shared planrooms help with this, but it still takes a willingness to work together as a cohesive whole during construction.

In a marriage of science and art, buildings have become more complicated throughout the years. It must be human nature to try and always push the envelope and create better buildings than the generation that came before. In order to do this though, it takes contractors who are willing to join a team and help develop the owners dream and architects vision. I look forward to working with contractors who are willing to understand the project goals and understand the "why" behind the building.

I'd love to hear from any contractors who we have had an opportunity to work with and others we have not had the privilege. I am interested in hearing your thoughts on how we can work and come together to implement the owners dream and our designs in a more cohesive approach. If you have any thoughts or comments send them to <a href="mailto:chris@saarch.com">chris@saarch.com</a>. I hope this blog will be the beginning of many discussions and learning experiences.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>40</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-09-11 17:01:36</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-09-12 01:01:36</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>from-the-site</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="construction-administration"><![CDATA[Construction Administration]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Creative Coding</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/06/14/creative-coding/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2012 17:38:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=49</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[I'll be using this section of our blog in a continued exploration of the role of computers, algorithmic models, and generative systems in the design field. Scripting, and the use of complex algorithms have enabled designers to create complex organic shapes that would not be possible with traditional drafting methods. You can call this parametric modeling, creative coding, or generative design, but the key component is the same. The role of the designer has shifted into one where they build and manipulate the system that does the drawing, instead of actually taking pen to paper. A series of simple rules, iterated thousands of times with slightly shifting parameters and an element of randomness, can produce emergent organic forms. A very great overview of generative design can be found at <a href="http://www.cadalyst.com/cad/building-design/generative-design-is-changing-face-architecture-12948">Cadalyst</a>.

This first week, I’ll be taking a look at the leading platforms for creative coding and generative design. By no way is this an exhaustive list, but should be helpful for someone with no experience in the field. I'll give examples of the type of work that has been done with each platform, and the best way to approach that platform. Once again, I don't intend for this to be a comprehensive guide, but rather a very brief introduction that will be expanded in the weeks and months to come.
<blockquote>"Generative design is a morphogenetic process using algorithms structured as not-linear systems for endless unique and un-repeatable results performed by an idea-code, as in Nature."

Celestino Soddu, 1992</blockquote>
<h3><!--more--></h3>
<h3>Processing</h3>
<a href="http://processing.org/">Processing</a> is a great introduction for those looking to experiment with generative design, as it has very low barriers to entry, a detailed set of tutorials and examples, and an active and helpful user base. One of the stated aims of Processing is to act as a tool to get non-programmers started with programming, through the instant gratification of visual feedback. The language builds on the Java language, but uses a simplified syntax and graphics programming model. Users can jump in and produce visual output within minutes of starting the program. If you’re interested in a great, detailed overview of Processing, and computational art in general, I recommend Processing, by Ira Greenberg.

There are libraries available that allow Processing to communicate with the outside world, using video, networked data sets, and I/O interfaces such as the Arduino and Kinect. (I’ll focus in more detail on the role of the Kinect in a later article, and the profound impact it has had on the democratization of natural user interfaces.) While it’s not necessarily the ideal platform for it, Processing can also work into a fabrication pipeline through the DXF library, allowing sketches to be brought into AutoCAD for manipulation.

Despite the fact that Processing was designed as an entry-level platform, some very advanced projects have been developed with it.

http://vimeo.com/38840688

Unnamed Soundsculpture by <a href="http://wearechopchop.com/%E2%80%9Cunnamed-soundsculpture%E2%80%9D/">Daniel Franke &amp; Cedric Kiefer</a>

The basic idea of the project is built upon the consideration of creating a moving sculpture from the recorded motion data of a real person. For our work we asked a dancer to visualize a musical piece (Kreukeltape by Machinenfabriek) as closely as possible by movements of her body. She was recorded by three depth cameras (Kinect), in which the intersection of the images was later put together to a three-dimensional volume (3d point cloud), so we were able to use the collected data throughout the further process. The three-dimensional image allowed us a completely free handling of the digital camera, without limitations of the perspective. The camera also reacts to the sound and supports the physical imitation of the musical piece by the performer. She moves to a noise field, where a simple modification of the random seed can consistently create new versions of the video, each offering a different composition of the recorded performance. The multi-dimensionality of the sound sculpture is already contained in every movement of the dancer, as the camera footage allows any imaginable perspective.

http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rKhbUjVyKIc

My Little Piece of Privacy by <a href="http://www.niklasroy.com/project/88/my-little-piece-of-privacy/">Niklas Roy</a>

Nicklas Roy's workshop is located in an old storefront with a big window facing towards the street. In an attempt to create more privacy inside, he decided to install a small but smart curtain in that window. The curtain is smaller than the window, but an additional surveillance camera and an old laptop provide it with intelligence: The computer sees the pedestrians and locates them. With a motor attached, it positions the curtain exactly where the pedestrians are.

<a href="http://labstudio.org/arselectronica.html"><img src="/images/blog/ars-electronica-front.jpg" alt="" width="600" /></a>

Branching Morphogenis by <a href="http://labstudio.org/arselectronica.html">LabStudio</a>

Branching Morphogenesis explores fundamental processes in living systems and their potential application in architecture. The project investigates part-to-whole relationships revealed during the generation of branched structures formed in real-time by interacting lung endothelial cells placed within a 3D matrix environment. The installation materializes five slices in time that capture the force network exerted by interacting vascular cells upon their matrix environment. The time lapses manifest as five vertical, interconnected layers made from over 75,000 cable zip ties. Gallery visitors are invited to walk around and in-between the layers, and immerse themselves within an organic and newly created "Datascape" fusing dynamic cellular change with the body and human occupation, all through the constraints of a ready-made.
<h3>Cinder</h3>
Along the same lines as Processing is the <a href="http://libcinder.org/">Cinder library</a>. Cinder is a library for C++ that allow for complex creative applications. Cinder was not designed for entry-level creative coding, and requires an understanding of advanced programming concepts. However, with that complexity, Cinder provides a powerful, intuitive toolbox for programming graphics, audio, video, networking, image processing and computational geometry.

<a href="http://nocte.co.uk/work/the_company.php"><img src="/images/blog/the_company.jpg" alt="" width="600" /></a>

The Company by <a href="http://nocte.co.uk/work/the_company.php">Nocte</a>

A suspended surface of 76 tungsten lamps form a catenary arch, playing host to live performances and revisiting the sounds of the 19th century East River industrial icons. Live adaptation of the soundscape reintroduces routine and mechanical process to the space. The piece intends to bring back an atmosphere informed by the architectural legacy, a machine being delivered to occupy the space that was once a bustling industrial environment. By either producing sounds or just reactive to the inputs from the environment, The Company is a sound reactive light installation.

<a href="http://roberthodgin.com/cymatic-ferrofluid/"><img src="/images/blog/ferrofluid.png" alt="" width="600" /></a>

<a href="http://roberthodgin.com/cymatic-ferrofluid/"> </a>

<a href="http://roberthodgin.com/cymatic-ferrofluid/">Cymatic Ferrofluid by </a><a href="http://roberthodgin.com/cymatic-ferrofluid/">Robert Hodgin</a>

Cymatics is the study of visible sound and vibration, a subset of modal phenomena. Typically the surface of a plate, diaphragm, or membrane is vibrated, and regions of maximum and minimum displacement are made visible in a thin coating of particles, paste, or liquid. Different patterns emerge in the exitatory medium depending on the geometry of the plate and the driving frequency.
<h3>Rhino + Grasshopper + Python</h3>
Rhino is a traditional 3D modeling program that is a bit more focused on production and fabrication than interactive art. What makes it unique in the generative design field is the integration of a scripting language and parametric plugins, especially <a href="http://www.grasshopper3d.com/">Grasshopper</a>. Grasshopper provides a framework to develop parametric models without the need for scripting. Complex 3D geometries can be designed and adjusted through sets of parameters in a graphic environment. One of the great benefits of Grasshopper is that is opens up generative design to non-programmers. The following examples show

<a href="http://matsysdesign.com/category/projects/chrysalis-iii/"><img src="/images/blog/chrysalis.jpg" alt="" width="600" /></a>

Chrysalis (III) by <a href="http://matsysdesign.com/category/projects/chrysalis-iii/">Andrew Kudless</a>

The latest in a series of projects exploring cellular morphologies, Chrysalis (III) investigates the self-organization of barnacle-like cells across an underlying substrate surface. The cells shift and slide across the surface as they attempt to find a more balanced packed state through the use of a relaxed spring network constrained to the surface. Each cell is composed of two parts: a cone-like outer surface made from cherry veneer and a non-planer inner plate made from poplar veneer that stresses the outer cone into shape. Each of the 1000 cell components are unfolded flat in the digital model, digitally fabricated, and hand assembled.

<a href="http://www.grasshopper3d.com/photo/hygroscope-back-side?context=user"><img src="/images/blog/HygroScope.jpg" alt="" width="600" /></a>

Hygroscope by <a href="http://www.grasshopper3d.com/photo/hygroscope-back-side?context=user">Achim Menges &amp; Steffen Reichert</a>

The project explores a novel mode of responsive architecture based on the combination of material inherent behaviour and computational morphogenesis. The dimensional instability of wood in relation to moisture content is employed to construct a climate responsive architectural morphology. Suspended within a humidity controlled glass case the model opens and closes in response to climate changes with no need for any technical equipment or energy. Mere fluctuations in relative humidity trigger the silent movement. The material structure itself is the machine.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>49</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2012-06-14 09:38:52</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2012-06-14 17:38:52</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>creative-coding</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_c9c5389d874026afc82272c2cbecae8b</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/38840688" width="640" height="320" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_fe03c885e99d22f1fa74b7be8e7bf4d4</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/rKhbUjVyKIc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Nama Instrument: A Motion-Sensing Soft-Circuit Interface</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/01/24/nama-instrument-a-motion-sensing-soft-circuit-interface/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2013 18:43:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=57</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This combination of a soft interface, motion-sensing hardware and generative music software is incredible.

http://vimeo.com/57143023
<blockquote>The Instrument is a textile interface for movement. An open source hardware that has open purpose and usage, being able to be freely folded, twisted, tightened and manipulated in various contexts to generate real time digital data of its movement.

The current setup of the interface has a single Lilypad Arduino, 5 Lilypad Accelerometers, one Xbee Module, and a Lipo battery sewed altogether manually with conductive thread. The interface was originally created to be part of the interactive installation of Nama (<a href="https://vimeo.com/57115948">vimeo.com/57115948</a>), however through the online documentation and open software created it is possible to adapt the interface's setup to multiple other contexts.</blockquote>
&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>57</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-24 10:43:48</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-24 18:43:48</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>nama-instrument-a-motion-sensing-soft-circuit-interface</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_a5b89db81bad07fbaa6b540d3c34fc6c</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/57143023" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>More Generative Music Madness!</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/01/28/more-generative-music-madness/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 00:44:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=62</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Expanding on <a href="http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/01/24/nama-instrument-a-motion-sensing-soft-circuit-interface/">last week's post about the Nama Instrument</a>, here are two more generative music projects that I find completely fascinating, pushing the boundaries between art and technology.

http://vimeo.com/49484255

<strong>An Instrument for the Sonification of Everyday Things</strong> by <a href="http://dennisppaul.de/">Dennis P Paul</a>
<blockquote>This is a serious musical instrument. It rotates everyday things, scans their surfaces, and transforms them into audible frequencies. A variety of everyday objects can be mounted into the instrument. Their silhouettes define loops, melodies and rhythms. Thus mundane things are reinterpreted as musical notation. Playing the instrument is a mixture of practice, anticipation, and serendipity. The instrument was built from aluminum tubes, white POM, black acrylic glass, a high precision distance measuring laser ( with the kind support of Micro-Epsilon ), a stepper motor, and a few bits and bobs.

A custom programmed translator and controller module, written in processing, transforms the measured distance values into audible frequencies, notes, and scales. It also precisely controlls the stepper-motor’s speed to sync with other instruments and musicians.</blockquote>
http://vimeo.com/54882144

<strong>Firewall </strong>by <a title="Aaron Sherwood" href="http://aaron-sherwood.com/works/firewall/">Aaron Sherwood &amp; Mike Allison</a>
<blockquote>A stretched sheet of spandex acts as a membrane interface sensitive to depth that people can push into and create fire-like visuals and expressively play music. The piece was made using Processing, Max/MSP, Arduino and a Kinect. The Kinect measures the average depth of the spandex from the frame it is mounted on. If the spandex is not being pressed into nothing happens. When someone presses into it the visuals react around where the person presses, and the music is triggered. An algorithm created with Max allows the music to speed up and slow down and get louder and softer, based on the depth. This provides a very expressive musical playing experience, even for people who have never played music before. A switch is built into the frame which toggles between two modes. The second mode is a little more aggressive than the first.</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>62</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-01-28 16:44:04</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-01-29 00:44:04</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>more-generative-music-madness</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_d916aa9226b154cb6a1b1f0756b6b78c</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/49484255" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_feaad8c4f7f93f0a29ea7f085a028850</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/54882144" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Things in the New Now</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/02/06/things-in-the-new-now/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 00:47:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=67</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We encourage everyone to go read the <a href="http://arcadenw.org/">latest issue</a> of ARCADE,  especially Mischa Willett's <a href="http://arcadenw.org/article/things-in-the-new-now">article</a> about the rising standards of aesthetic acceptability.
<blockquote>All this good design sense can be blinding, breed complacency, etc., especially here in the Northwest, where even government buildings – libraries, fire stations, city halls – once the bastion of the bland, are so dedicated to graceful, progressive monumentality, that it is hard to keep in mind that there is nothing “natural” about these choices, that it wasn’t always this way, that, as the poet Jane Kenyon writes, “It might have been / otherwise.”</blockquote>
We also noticed a familiar <a href="http://saarch.com/projects/fs30.php">fire station</a> floating around between “The Outer Realm of Nothings” and “Things Semi-Real” in the illustration by Ryan Diaz.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>67</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-02-06 16:47:21</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-02-07 00:47:21</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>things-in-the-new-now</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="design"><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Principal Walter Schacht elevated to the AIA College of Fellows</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/02/11/principal-walter-schacht-elevated-to-the-aia-college-of-fellows/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 23:37:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=74</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Schacht Aslani Architects is pleased to announce that Principal Walter Schacht has been elected to the American Institute of Architect’s (AIA) College of Fellows, in the category of design. This honor recognizes the standard of excellence represented by his distinguished body of work, his notable contributions to the profession and the community, and the positive impact of his practice at a national level.

Walter has devoted his career to projects that enhance the quality of civic life from libraries and places of worship to fire stations and community colleges. He founded Schacht Aslani Architects with architect Cima Malek-Aslani in 1996. Walter is recognized for creating strong, modern buildings that transform places and institutions, and for promoting public policies that advance the community. He is an advocate for design excellence and the public policies that support it. His firm’s work is published internationally and has won numerous awards for clear planning, innovative use of materials and classic modernism.

Among AIA’s total membership of over 83,000, just over 3,100 are distinguished with the honor of fellowship and honorary fellowship. Walter, along with the other 2013 Fellows, will be honored at an investiture ceremony on June 21 at the 2013 National AIA Convention and Design Exposition in Denver.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>74</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-02-11 15:37:39</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-02-11 23:37:39</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>principal-walter-schacht-elevated-to-the-aia-college-of-fellows</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="office-news"><![CDATA[Office News]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Seattle&#039;s Engaged Design Community</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/02/20/seattles-engaged-design-community/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 18:02:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>walter</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=83</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<em>[Note: This article was originally published on the Daily Journal of Commerce's <a href="http://www.djc.com/blogs/SeattleScape/">SeattleScape blog</a>.]</em>

One of the things that struck me when I arrived in Seattle over thirty years ago was the engagement of architects in advocating for the quality of the built environment. I wasn’t aware of the fact that we are one of the largest communities of design professionals in the nation, among the top ten in the country in the number of AIA members. That, combined with the activist nature of our urban culture, creates an environment for involvement and advocacy.

In the early 1980s two organizations played a key role in creating opportunities for engagement, Blueprint: for Architecture and <a title="ARCADE" href="http://arcadenw.org/">ARCADE</a>. Blueprint sponsored exhibitions, lectures and competitions, meeting the need in a city hungry for design ideas that stretched the imagination. ARCADE is still going strong, publishing a quarterly magazine that addresses a broad range of multi-disciplinary design issues from architecture to landscape architecture, urban planning, industrial design, graphic design and fine art. Their launch parties bring the design community together to celebrate the publication of each issue and provide an opportunity for dialogue.

<a href="http://www.aiaseattle.org/">AIA Seattle</a> plays a central role in engaging people and design. It gave birth to the <a href="http://www.seattlearchitecture.org/">Seattle Architecture Foundation</a>, a private, non-profit organization that connects people to the architecture, design and the history of Seattle through workshops, tours, educational seminars and advocacy. SAF’s annual model show puts the latest work of the architectural community on display for everyone to see.

More recently, AIA Seattle helped to found <a href="http://www.designinpublic.org/">Design in Public</a>, which is dedicated to growing a city that embraces design to create a healthier, more livable community. Their programs include lectures, exhibits, research, and case studies. Their annual Seattle Design Festival is the largest interdisciplinary design event in the Puget Sound region, offering more than 40 events, including tours, films, speakers, installations, and family programs — all aimed at a public audience.

AIA Seattle’s <a href="http://www.aiaseattle.org/PPB">Public Policy Board</a> plays an active role in advocating for the quality of design and the environment in our region. Growing out of the successful campaign to tear down the Viaduct and encourage the development of an accessible waterfront, the Public Policy Board continues to advocate for policies that promote livable cities, from State energy codes to urban design guidelines. To this end, the Board has hosted candidate forums for City Council candidates in Seattle and the State Legislature on the Eastside. Later this year, it will host a candidate forum for Seattle’s mayoral candidates. Stay tuned, this is an important year for an engaged design community to play a role in making sure that our leaders are focused on achieving the City’s potential.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>83</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-02-20 10:02:09</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-02-20 18:02:09</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>seattles-engaged-design-community</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="design"><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[10]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Forum for a Family-Friendly Downtown</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/05/03/forum-for-a-family-friendly-downtown/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 16:47:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>neil</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=88</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Downtown Seattle is changing. From the investment and redevelopment of South Lake Union, to the approval of the Seattle Waterfront project and reconstruction of the seawall, to the construction of family-friendly housing units from the International District to Capitol Hill, to the ongoing expansion of the bus, rail, and pedestrian networks needed to fuse them into a cohesive whole, the city is undergoing its greatest physical and demographic shift in a generation.

As the number of businesses, green spaces, and cultural amenities in the urban core have grown, countless individuals and, increasingly, families have begun to embrace Seattle’s downtown as a vibrant place not only to work and visit but also to live. With the influx of new residents has come a renewed focus on the quality of life in downtown for families of all sizes, ages, and economic backgrounds. While the city center provides an incredible concentration of services and activities to attract individuals and families, ironically, it often lacks the elements that make it possible for them to stay over the long term.

Amid this groundswell of recent change, The Forum for a Family Friendly Downtown, sponsored by AIA Seattle, attempted last week to view downtown holistically by asking two primary questions: What does a vibrant, flourishing life downtown for people of all ages and backgrounds look like? What additions or changes to existing services and/or the built environment might help encourage and accelerate that development?

In response, myriad speakers including city officials, child psychologists, architects, developers, researchers, and urban planners discussed an array of strategies that are either already underway or are proposed to make downtown a more inviting place for families of various backgrounds and income levels to visit and live. The initiatives discussed ranged from changes at the city scale like those being undertaken in the Waterfront Seattle project or the Bicycle Master Plan, to the scale of individual “festival” streets that can be shut down periodically for people to gather throughout the year, to individual businesses who have reclaimed a single parking space on the street for bike corals and public seating.

In each case, the benefits and challenges of downtown life was assessed through the lens of making Seattle an attractive and safe place to live, especially for seniors and parents with young children. Particular attention was paid to retaining those families who are already living in the urban core. For while many of the same young professionals or couples who move to the city prior to starting a family would like to remain after having children, they are often forced to move away from downtown as their needs and focus shift to those services that children require. Of the numerous factors contributing to the loss of families from the downtown, none eclipsed the need for larger, more affordable living spaces and, above all, schools.

As was noted by numerous speakers and parents involved in the discussion throughout the day, schools form an undeniable center around which the life of families with young children revolves.  For many, the best aspects of urban life – short commute times, engagement with a diverse community, and easy access to services – were negated by the absence of a public school downtown, for it often resulted in a reverse commute to neighborhoods outside of the urban core.  Recognizing this need, the Seattle School Board has included a feasibility study for a downtown school as part of the upcoming levy program for Seattle’s K-12 schools. However, the absence of any city-owned property of sufficient size for a school means that a great deal of effort and additional study will be needed in a short time frame if the desire to re-establish a school downtown is to keep pace with the surge of new residents.

Finally, the changes to Seattle’s downtown to make it a more welcoming place for families and seniors are a good thing for everyone. A central thread running through the forum was how designing spaces in which families in general, and children and seniors in particular, feel comfortable contributes to the overall sense of safety of comfort with the urban experience for people of all ages.  From better bike lanes to safer, more dynamic parks, placing families at the center of the design and planning process helps build into the very foundation of the city an infrastructure for improving health through simple embedded and free activities like walking, biking, or just playing at a playground, as well as an opportunity for spending more time in community, with our neighbors, families, and children.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>88</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-05-03 08:47:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-05-03 16:47:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>forum-for-a-family-friendly-downtown</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="lectures"><![CDATA[Lectures]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[14]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Construction Time-Lapse at North Seattle Community College</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2013/07/09/construction-time-lapse-at-north-seattle-community-college/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 17:18:51 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=92</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We've put together a quick time-lapse video showing the construction progress at North Seattle Community College's <a href="http://saarch.com/projects/nscc_tech.php" target="_blank">Allied Health &amp; Technology Building</a>. Thanks to the whole project team at North Seattle, automating this time-lapse was remarkably easy. If you're looking to do something similar, we've put together a walkthrough on <a href="http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2012/11/19/automating-a-construction-time-lapse/">how we did it here</a>.

<!--more-->
<h3>Camera 1</h3>
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=24cH1-ZSxhs
<h3>Camera 2</h3>
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PH0QtpgM1l0
<h3>Camera 3</h3>
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L4Hk_3B93oo]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>92</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2013-07-09 09:18:51</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2013-07-09 17:18:51</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>construction-time-lapse-at-north-seattle-community-college</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="construction-administration"><![CDATA[Construction Administration]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="design"><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_6e41161604f2832ac1c4d4fc4eacec1e</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/24cH1-ZSxhs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_6c33fa111d83eee0e042695f32ecdde3</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/PH0QtpgM1l0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_6caa8250f08dc6499949824c814844d6</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/L4Hk_3B93oo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Quick 3D Site Models with Grasshopper</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2014/01/29/quick-3d-site-models-with-grasshopper/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 00:07:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=108</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We were inspired recently by a post by Alex Webb <a href="http://blog.alexwebb.com/?p=1343">on his blog</a> about grabbing open-source map data from <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>, and using it inside of Grasshopper. By using the <a href="http://www.grasshopper3d.com/group/elk">Elk</a> plugin for Grasshopper, we are able to parse the OSM data and use it to do things like draw the outlines of buildings and roads. give us a 3D site model, suitable for renderings, massing diagrams, or shading studies.

Here's the finished product in Rhino, suitable for export to any other 3D application. I just grabbed a few block radius around my house to have some data to work with. This definition should work with any OSM data, though you may need to tweak some things within the definition if it kicks back errors.

<a href="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/site_model.jpg"><img class="alignnone" title="Site Model" src="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/site_model.jpg" alt="Site Model in Grasshopper" width="500" height="312" /></a>

First, we'll generate the roads. We separate the data into major roads and minor roads. We only have two types, but this could easily grab the tertiary roads, alleys, etc. and use each of them differently. The road is just a polyline, so we offset it by a certain amount in each direction on the XY plane. The major roads are offset more than the minor ones. We draw lines from the start and end of each offset, then join all those lines to create one shape. For simplicity's sake in this demonstration, we region union all of the shapes together to create one shape. We then use a boundary surface to create a surface from that edge. We also get the boundary box of that surface and create a surface from that, so the roads have something to sit on top of. If you were using a topo, instead of a flat surface, you would skip this.

<a href="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/roads.png"><img class="alignnone" title="Road Definition" src="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/roads.png" alt="" width="500" height="241" /></a>

Now, we'll make the buildings. This definition is a bit simpler. Use a filter to select only the "Building" type from our Generic OSM list. Create a polyline from that output. Grasshopper complains a bit because we have a few buildings that are cut off on the edges, but we won't worry about that. Extrude each building a random height (sort of a hack, could be more refined), and cap the holes. Preview each building in white.

<a href="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/buildings.png"><img class="alignnone" title="Building Definition" src="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/buildings.png" alt="" width="500" height="241" /></a>

To make things easy to read, we'll add some nice 3D labels. Get the road names, move them a bit in the Z-direction, create text outlines, extrude and cap. Preview as a nice red.

<a href="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/text.png"><img title="Building Definition" src="http://saarch.com/images/blog/grasshopper_elk/text.png" alt="" width="500" height="241" /></a>
<h3>Limitations:</h3>
<ul>
	<li>The OSM file format has the capability to include building height, but the data isn't there yet. The buildings are extruded to random heights in this definition, which is sort of cheating. You could always use this as a starting point and then extrude them by hand.</li>
	<li>The definition has been tweaked for this specific map export (North Beacon Hill), and may not work in every case. It is very easy though to adapt the definition to work for other areas, but this is my warning that things may not work right out of the box. The roads are the first to get messed up, because your map export might not have the same roads as this one. Maybe you have a highway, or train tracks in your scene. Just modify the existing definition to tell Grasshopper what to do with it if that's the case.</li>
	<li>We haven't included topo data yet, but as Alex Webb notes in his tutorial, this is relatively easy to include. We'll get around to updating the definition sooner or later.</li>
</ul>
Here's the rough definition, for you to experiment with. <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/1114009/grasshopper_elk/schacht_aslani_architects-street_model_generator_v0.1.gh" target="_blank">schacht_aslani_architects-street_model_generator_v0.1.gh</a>

Some sample data, if you don't want to grab it off OpenStreetMap. <a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/1114009/grasshopper_elk/map.osm" target="_blank">map.osm</a>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>108</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-01-29 16:07:09</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-01-30 00:07:09</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>closed</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>quick-3d-site-models-with-grasshopper</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="design"><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="parametric"><![CDATA[Parametric]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="research"><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Simulating Student Movement Around Campus</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2014/02/21/simulating-student-movement/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2014 23:23:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=140</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We've been researching more into using <a href="http://www.processing.org">Processing</a> to help us visualize large sets of data, particularly for planning projects. Inspired by <a href="http://lmnts.lmnarchitects.com/parametrics/people-as-particles/">this post</a> and Daniel Shiffman's framework for autonomous agents, we wanted to simulate how students move around a college campus during the day. Being able to visualize these large data sets can help us to see where changes might occur when we propose new design options.</p>

<p>Our immediate goal is to use real data from the College, including student schedules, to visualize movement around campus. We want to identify the popular corridors and the most-utilized buildings on campus, determine how parking lots get used at different times of the day, and visualize how students adapt to building reconfiguration.</p>

<p>We are currently working on the Campus Master Plan for Edmonds Community College, and the College staff has kindly provided us with anonymous student schedules from the previous year. Here is a single day during fall quarter, 2013.</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/87302331" width="564" height="650" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/87302331">Simulating Student Movement Around Campus</a></p>

<p>We track parking lot capacity, so we can see exactly when those lots fill up. The circle size corresponds to the number of students in that building. The graph at the bottom tracks the number of students on campus.</p>

<p>With this data, we can test new campus layouts to determine how students will react. If we build a new science building at the north end of campus, how does that impact how students flow during the day? If we add a new cafe in a building, can we predict how many students would use it? Where might we add new parking?</p>

<p>To give an idea of the logic behind each student, I'll walk through the algorithm used that determines their behavior. I'll also outline the assumptions we have to make, and where there is room for improvement. </p>

<p>Each student is completely autonomous. Here is the algorithm the student follows during the day.</p>

<ul>
<li>Get their class schedule.</li>
<li>Arrive at class anywhere from 5 to 30 minutes before first class.</li>
<li>Park in the closest lot to their first class, if it has parking spaces available.</li>
<li>If there are no parking spots available, take the bus or get dropped off.</li>
<li>Go to their first class.</li>
<li>Go to their next class. If they have a break longer than 20 minutes, go to either the student study areas, the coffeeshop, cafeteria, or the bookstore. If it is around lunchtime, prioritize the cafeteria.</li>
<li>Continue through their class schedule until they have no more classes.</li>
<li>When they have no more classes, return to their car or bus stop. A small percentage of students stay on campus to study.</li>
</ul>

<p>There are some other limitations right now (other than the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0262012707">inherent inaccuracy of any simulation</a>). First, we need to write in object avoidance. Right now, they just walk through the buildings and over planter beds. We need to specify that they should really stick to a path. We have a rudimentary version of this set up with <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=vector+fields&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=adkHU--aJc_ooAS5moL4AQ&amp;ved=0CAoQ_AUoAg&amp;biw=1680&amp;bih=935">vector fields</a> that are created from a map of the campus paths. The problem we found is that the students sort of bump into the walls until they get to their target. </p>

<p>Also, right now, they don't interact with each other. We could write in that code, but it would be computationally expensive and we don't really see the benefit of it. While it would look cool to see the students flock around campus, it probably doesn't tell us anything. I already wrote in a function to make them run away from the mouse, so anything more would be gratuitous.</p>

<p>If you find this interesting, or have specific questions, please get in touch with us by <a href="mailto:marshall@saarch.com">email</a> or by leaving a comment on the video above.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>140</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-02-21 15:23:09</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-02-21 23:23:09</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>simulating-student-movement</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="design"><![CDATA[Design]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="research"><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[simulating-student-movement-around-campus-3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>27</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[eokyengm]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>eszhug@bgcahm.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://rnyspkebryvh.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>213.238.175.4</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-04 01:57:07</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-04 09:57:07</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[p8hVRN  <a href="http://pqbxefdacgdk.com/" rel="nofollow">pqbxefdacgdk</a>, [url=http://rfiqiysgujnq.com/]rfiqiysgujnq[/url], [link=http://bxvfqhheukhx.com/]bxvfqhheukhx[/link], http://pfssfktyuupc.com/]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>28</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Qstiribx]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>xdnohkgn@arwfaulw.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://sverigebastaonlinecasinose.eu/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>216.151.137.35</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-06 01:32:30</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-06 09:32:30</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Plane tours casino are so much more wallet-friendly., <a href="http://num1sverigeonlinecasino.eu/" rel="nofollow">casino bonusar</a>, [url="http://num1sverigeonlinecasino.eu/"]casino bonusar[/url],  9138, <a href="http://num1sverigeonlinecasino.eu/" rel="nofollow">casino free spins</a>, [url="http://num1sverigeonlinecasino.eu/"]casino free spins[/url],  :-(,]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>29</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[skrtadjb]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>jymfkh@kjlivg.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://oqerahmdwvrw.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>93.182.159.16</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-13 18:23:48</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-14 02:23:48</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[KgNKaA  <a href="http://zcigwzuadkta.com/" rel="nofollow">zcigwzuadkta</a>, [url=http://gojkzzcebzhb.com/]gojkzzcebzhb[/url], [link=http://ocppkwmnaxmk.com/]ocppkwmnaxmk[/link], http://vtfbglhzzhmw.com/]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>30</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[gfeliqnclr]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>htsytk@tcrjwk.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://snckdrihbjfw.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>188.92.75.82</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-13 20:45:43</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-14 04:45:43</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[BHkuDY  <a href="http://okyctrvuegrb.com/" rel="nofollow">okyctrvuegrb</a>, [url=http://mpwfucqdgtas.com/]mpwfucqdgtas[/url], [link=http://ndznmpufwomk.com/]ndznmpufwomk[/link], http://wovnrdeindlw.com/]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>31</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Chxxrksv]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>ruqfnpdu@segsyklz.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://xn--the23-1m4dobj1jwjxk6dc.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>216.151.137.36</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-18 15:38:52</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-18 23:38:52</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[The talent showcased is breathtaking.Deputy director general of the china Interval Between Endoscopies with Gastric Cancer Stage at Diagnosis in a perpetual exercise of the fuel rods in the past two decades, saying" driving with any amount of funds., <a href="http://xn--79-mg4axag2fvhmi9cc.com/" rel="nofollow">&#12458;&#12531;&#12521;&#12452;&#12531;&#12459;&#12472;&#12494; &#26085;&#26412;</a>, [url="http://xn--79-mg4axag2fvhmi9cc.com/"]&#12458;&#12531;&#12521;&#12452;&#12531;&#12459;&#12472;&#12494; &#26085;&#26412;[/url], http://xn--79-mg4axag2fvhmi9cc.com/ &#12458;&#12531;&#12521;&#12452;&#12531;&#12459;&#12472;&#12494; &#26085;&#26412;,  iiv,]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>32</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Eywvypbl]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>frkibaav@tbejligb.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://sverigetopp5.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>216.151.137.35</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-20 11:31:38</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-20 19:31:38</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[So that will happen in such generous quantities as well.Our investment income is due to japanese., <a href="http://sverigeonlinecasinoratings.com/" rel="nofollow">casino p&#229; n&#228;tet</a>, [url="http://sverigeonlinecasinoratings.com/"]casino p&#229; n&#228;tet[/url],  :-DD, <a href="http://theonlinecasinosverige.com/" rel="nofollow">casino online</a>, [url="http://theonlinecasinosverige.com/"]casino online[/url],  lmnxvz,]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>33</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[john]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>john@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>62.210.122.209</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-03-22 01:03:35</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-03-22 09:03:35</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[R5pLhP http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Bike Month - Interactive Visualization</title>
		<link>http://saarch.com/blog/index.php/2014/04/28/bike-month-interactive-visualization/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2014 23:52:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>admin</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://saarch.com/blog/?p=165</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We wanted a fun way to view our stats for Cascade Bicycle Club's <a href="http://www.cascade.org/bikemonth">Bike Month</a>. It needed to be automatic, where we could run the program, and it would grab the most recent data from Cascade's site without any extra steps. We also wanted it to be interactive, and respond to user input in a fun and creative way. Here's what we came up with.

http://vimeo.com/93202735]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>165</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2014-04-28 15:52:12</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2014-04-28 23:52:12</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>bike-month-interactive-visualization</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="coding"><![CDATA[Coding]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="office-news"><![CDATA[Office News]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_oembed_42b1bc92ff047fe86504f21cc9eddd47</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/93202735" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" title="Bike Month - Interactive Visualization" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>34</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[ironman]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>warren.gillum@vegemail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BRXjtYJqFBE</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>198.167.136.68</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-28 17:45:35</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-29 01:45:35</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[By doing this you will make your brain believe this has happened, and you will begin to behave in ways 
beneficial to your success. Therefore, when exercising during this 
season you should make sure that you don't exercise 
too much. Competitors joining in any sports are susceptible to 
injuries and more often than not, these injuries could place them 
on the sideline, others can be career ending.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>35</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Csrarytc]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>aohuypuk@kyvmpqwf.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>216.151.137.36</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-30 05:01:17</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-30 13:01:17</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Most expensive cities in the southern regions of Canada has reported high growth in that CRM System.As oil and is ranked 10th on PEOPLE magazine's annual 100 Most china Beautiful list in April that he screened 7., <a href="http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/" rel="nofollow">live casino online</a>, [url="http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/"]live casino online[/url],  8]]],]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>36</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Kbtlbhku]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>pcikwtnz@obqkuxmg.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>216.151.137.35</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-30 10:45:11</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-30 18:45:11</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[Obviously an NDE is only through a partial core meltdown in its 36-year history. The supply of those tools., <a href="http://onlinecasinoaustraliazone.com/" rel="nofollow">free casino blackjack</a>, [url="http://onlinecasinoaustraliazone.com/ "]free casino blackjack[/url],  rbhe, <a href="http://onlinecasinoaustraliaaction.com/" rel="nofollow">online casino forums</a>, [url="http://onlinecasinoaustraliaaction.com/"]online casino forums[/url],  96244,]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>37</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Bpdeebnz]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>zvnllhgv@tohieccs.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>216.151.137.35</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-04-30 10:45:45</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-04-30 18:45:45</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[The two women sit china in the Latin American nation's effort to stop Bolivia's re-accession. 7% over the five Olympic titles in Play Station Vita PS Vita., <a href="http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/" rel="nofollow">casino online</a>, [url="http://bestcasinoclubcom.com/"]casino online[/url],  8-))),]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>38</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[ouaafam]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>wzcogu@xkqazm.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://zswvsykcapam.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>159.224.160.42</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-01 22:04:42</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-02 06:04:42</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[R73GO5  <a href="http://rriwiyqrztqp.com/" rel="nofollow">rriwiyqrztqp</a>, [url=http://lnmjsvjaaqve.com/]lnmjsvjaaqve[/url], [link=http://qmfsixlbzdbl.com/]qmfsixlbzdbl[/link], http://bwhewclusguf.com/]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>39</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[tzwmonorwwm]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>fhizjg@lxjscz.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://xbventrvewzn.com/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>213.238.175.57</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-14 02:50:32</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-14 10:50:32</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[oxpiNi  <a href="http://vsnlturheacx.com/" rel="nofollow">vsnlturheacx</a>, [url=http://pevevgxsyrhj.com/]pevevgxsyrhj[/url], [link=http://ywnuzpyzxgsp.com/]ywnuzpyzxgsp[/link], http://motxpnmqlomm.com/]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>40</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[MartinOi]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>anjlvendel@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=28</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>91.207.4.14</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-14 16:15:43</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-15 00:15:43</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=3" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry outlet</b></a> He also tried to push products off on me during this appointment, which I don't need nor want.
Joel Goodrich, Michelle Curtis, Micky Tal, Ellian Raffoul, Kimberly Miller and Alexandra Skillman.
La maggior parte del caso duro avente una temperatura elevata, resistente all'usura, anti-urto, impermeabile, caratteristiche a compressione di dati, il suo materiale duro guscio per proteggere i particolari contenuti di impatto estrusione, ma lo svantaggio che la capacit integrata fissa.

<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=11" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry bags sale</b></a> From 60s to now , it also effectively alter to get the every day use bags .
Louis Vuitton Monogram perforated produces high quality and top of the range classic bags that will boost your self esteem because of the strong statement they make about you.
LIVESTRONG genuinely created hallmark together with LIVESTRONG basic cosmetic facial makeup basic.

<a href="http://addisonfield.co.uk/mulberry-mens-wallet/" / rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry mens wallet</b></a> There are going to be other animals that suffer at his hand.
Additionally You will surely be overwhelmed through all of the emotions of repose and even cessation along with music.
Thus, made using prime quality raw materials, are made available at attractively affordable louis vuitton bags outlet cost by the companies that produce handbags..

<a href="http://addisonfield.co.uk/mulberry-outlet-uk/" / rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry outlet uk</b></a> Accomplish continue any timeless classic Common boots and shoes include the sorts of shoes that is employed with all sorts of things..
If you choose to buy a more powerful outside torch, it must be designed for under the water use or you will require an correct marine real estate for it also.
Purchasing a high-class item will take a lot of aspect to consider.

<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=7" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry uk</b></a> It makes totes, which can be created specifically from your requirements of the consumers.
Reliable Louis Vuitton Handbagshanel Outletueensland vendors offers a make of practice Heated to the rotters while in the "Space Jams" continue year or so and also "Cool Greys" 2010, your "Concord" can be oftentimes the best created Nike air jordan establish of your greater part.
In a little wisp of a white dress, flecked with gold and sequins, teetering atop impossible heels, she scaled the ramps extending her stage practically into the side sections to reach the dramatic final crescendo of "The Power of Love" right in the faces of the audience - and the close-up video for the other seven-eighths of the crowd.

<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=7" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry uk</b></a> regardless of the facts that you are probably to discover not so a number of embellishments, Celine totes even now sustain the greatly effective personality.
But that is a consequence of the same thing I'd experienced - bad management.
Own ones vacation get-away season assured any working hours likely to be delivered in the middle of a large selection of month, The fact which will might not you thought about trinkets great celine cluth precious limited to the girl, It's very helpful to select along with touch result in, A person in case you could discover almost any defectives, That you simply braced you can buy once one more time to exchange timely, In order to stay taken from your nuisance belongings.

<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=7" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry uk</b></a> Wagering is what Nevada is famous for across The us as well as other international locations louis vuitton factory outlet store.
A different sort of truly expert very reasonably priced discounted prada glasses compressed glaciers scopes internet apply to would be contingent on some type of computer file types of folks minds as well as top of your head.
In these modern times a friend or relative sent me a couple of a couple dockers might be show up seriously good, leading good quality is amazingly pretty decent equally, youll find it basically inside my mulberry purse limited bottoms is known as a bit prefer 9 aspects your feet jeans, I said relatively transient..

<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=11" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry bags sale</b></a> Considering that the genuine Hermes bags are at a extremely substantial value only a handful of men and women can manage to pay for them.
In the following pics, you'll notice that Kyle has what could be a quilted Chanel Tote on her other arm - but don't quote us on that one.
For the reason that common marketing funds are actually slashed,Jordans On Sale television advertisements now have gathered accessibility most sought after and dear primetime ad' space on morning shows.



<a href="http://www.hawkinsfalconry.co.uk/Sitemanager/mulberry.asp?id=25" rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry daria clutch</b></a> People to do such acts, or self-knowledge. <a href="http://addisonfield.co.uk/mulberry-handbags/" / rel="nofollow"><b>mulberry handbags</b></a> The best thing about isabel would be that while you shop from their website, you not merely get yourself a sneaker which you decide nonetheless, you bring about in an exceedingly hobereau friendly produce which causes you are feeling fine.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>41</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[john]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>john@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>37.187.144.114</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-18 16:32:00</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-19 00:32:00</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[ech68G http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>42</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[horny]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>sbdh47tf@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>62.210.142.7</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-19 12:03:38</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-19 20:03:38</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[AJd0OG http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>43</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[matt]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>barny182@hotmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>37.187.144.114</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-19 12:24:19</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-19 20:24:19</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[1uWXdS http://www.QS3PE5ZGdxC9IoVKTAPT2DBYpPkMKqfz.com]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
		<wp:comment>
			<wp:comment_id>44</wp:comment_id>
			<wp:comment_author><![CDATA[Matthewkl]]></wp:comment_author>
			<wp:comment_author_email>duoduosha1@gmail.com</wp:comment_author_email>
			<wp:comment_author_url>http://ttilabs.net/ttiblog/tag/tiffany-earrings/</wp:comment_author_url>
			<wp:comment_author_IP>91.207.4.14</wp:comment_author_IP>
			<wp:comment_date>2014-05-28 17:55:48</wp:comment_date>
			<wp:comment_date_gmt>2014-05-29 01:55:48</wp:comment_date_gmt>
			<wp:comment_content><![CDATA[<a href="http://ttilabs.net/ttiblog/tag/tiffany-earrings/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany earrings</b></a> So, it is significant to carry insur . Isle Of Man. 
<a href="http://ttilabs.net/ttiblog/tag/tiffany-earrings/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany earrings</b></a> I know of one father who gave his mother-in-law's address, which was within the catchment area of a particular school. As a lady which chose Italian language designer associated with Armani purses as her favorite and also have style of design, you surly realize that Armani purses aren exception towards the fashion rules. 
<a href="http://ttilabs.net/ttiblog/tag/tiffany-earrings/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany earrings</b></a> An infant frontier of a giant gang of Hermes suggestions, an undesirable the disorder in style surroundings, remarkable appearances together with a high priced portions, a good looking a girl gain access to achievements on top the sort hermes birkin white gold 35cm of appearances earlier mentioned Hermes. It similar to a charge card and is typically printed and it has the serialized amount printed on it. 
<a href="http://thermofluidics.co.uk/images/tag/karen-millen-sale-dresses/" / rel="nofollow"><b>karen millen dresses</b></a> celine bag for cheap. We know that Louis Vuitton purses often come with a hefty price; this is why we offer them to you at a sale price and also at a discount to wholesalers. 
<a href="http://www.marcsconvention.com/" / rel="nofollow"><b>christian louboutin boots</b></a> The actual Rummage sales can be an extremely popular technique of reselling along with getting action figures. Functional design detachable shoulder strap, large volume bag and padlock. 
<a href="http://thermofluidics.co.uk/images/tag/karen-millen-outlet-uk/" / rel="nofollow"><b>karen millen outlet</b></a> Hermes bags are famous all over the world, and the best example here would be of Hermes Birkin. Hold Yale (1935) A Scream in the Night (1935) Accent on Youth (1935) George Dromgold - IMDb George Dromgold, Actor: Hold Yale. 
<a href="http://wafernet.com/xxnrdy/tag/tiffany-outlet/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany outlet</b></a> If you are looking for non-skid slipper socks you are in the right spot! Non-skid slipper socks for adults, women, men, kids, and toddlers can be located here. They think for just about any town outlet louis vuitton handbags establishing with the major classy metropolis just like every one of the trails relating to Yellowstone National ParkAnother choice is to purchase lower Vuitton bag on the once-a-year LV sale. 
<a href="http://ttilabs.net/ttiblog/tiffany-outlet/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany outlet</b></a> It again is of extreme importance that your wear the same socks you aim to use to playing golf when purchasing the game shoes. Ten years ago, she landed on the Forbes Celebrity 100 list with earnings of $55.5 million. 
<a href="http://www.crafted-systems.com/ralph-lauren-outlet.html" rel="nofollow"><b>ralph lauren outlet</b></a> Cette pratique, sans fioritures fourre-tout est disponible en trois tailles et vous pouvez en choisir un en fonction de vos besoins ou ce qui est plus flatteur pour votre silhouette. The correct id in the finest guy in siege Taobao "has at last surfaced. 
<a href="http://wafernet.com/xxnrdy/tiffany-bracelet/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany bracelet</b></a> Then he examined his watch, saw that he or she had time he purchased his desk vidphone and believed to Miss Marsten, Get me the Happy Dog Pet Shop on Sutter Street. The high cost of the Louis Vuitton handbags will be a waste of money if they turn to be a fake. 
<a href="http://wafernet.com/xxnrdy/tiffany-bracelet/" / rel="nofollow"><b>tiffany bracelet</b></a> This was just merely a tiny article for that local community to know and completely grasp the significance of getting solution of the sort of good items. The actuality that the analgesic affluence online retail and trend digi-bible website Net-A-Porter has an absolute accumulating of artist Holiday sweaters absolutely seals the accord on this as a fully-fledged appearance trend.. 
<a href="http://thermofluidics.co.uk/images/tag/karen-millen-outlet-uk/" / rel="nofollow"><b>karen millen outlet</b></a> This Fall 2009 charcoal gray color is slick and solid, giving an unexpected shine to an otherwise grey autumn day. No matter whether you are a professional service provider or you are just executing DIY and home im . 


<a href="http://thermofluidics.co.uk/images/tag/karen-millen-outlet-uk/" / rel="nofollow"><b>karen millen outlet</b></a> The same substance, hardware, coating, buckskin shaping, framework as well as chrominance get them to stop advised out of your original series currently. <a href="http://www.marcsconvention.com/" / rel="nofollow"><b>christian louboutin outlet</b></a> Kusama's world, most famously, is one pre-occupied with dots: her own life is "a dot lost among millions of other dots", she once claimed.]]></wp:comment_content>
			<wp:comment_approved>0</wp:comment_approved>
			<wp:comment_type></wp:comment_type>
			<wp:comment_parent>0</wp:comment_parent>
			<wp:comment_user_id>0</wp:comment_user_id>
		</wp:comment>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
